<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jdb@mail.nerc-essc.ac.uk">Jon Blower</author>
    <title>Styx Grid Services</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="What are Styx Grid Services?">
      <p>Styx Grid Services (SGSs) are a means for wrapping command-line programs and
      allowing them to be used remotely over the Internet.  When deployed as an SGS,
      a program can be run from anywhere on the Internet <em>exactly as if it
      were a local program</em>.</p>
      <p>SGSs can be composed into &quot;workflows&quot;, in which a number of
      SGSs, perhaps in different locations, can be combined using very simple
      shell scripts to create distributed applications.  Data can be streamed
      directly between the services along the shortest network path.</p>
      <p><a href="http://www.resc.rdg.ac.uk/publications/posters/sgs_poster_SC2005.pdf">This poster</a>
      is a good summary of the main capabilities of the SGS system.
      <a href="http://www.resc.rdg.ac.uk/publications/Blower_et_al_ICCS06.pdf">This paper</a>
      is a more detailed description of the capabilites of the SGS system.</p>
      
      <subsection name="A simple example">
      <p>Let us consider a simple distributed application, consisting of two Styx Grid Services.
      The first is called <tt>calc_mean</tt> and reads a set of input files
      from a set of scientific experiments, calculates their mean and outputs the
      result as a file.  The second SGS is called <tt>plot</tt> and it might be
      deployed in a completely different location from the first service. It takes a single
      input data file and turns it into a graph. The shell script (workflow) that
      would be used to take a set of input files, calculate their mean
      and plot a graph of the result would be:</p>
      <source>calc_mean input*.dat -o mean.dat
plot -i mean.dat -o graph.gif</source>
      <p>The important thing to note is that this is <em>exactly the same script</em> as
      would be used to run the programs if they were installed locally.  The input files
      for each service have been detected and uploaded automatically and the output files
      have been automatically downloaded.</p>
      <p>The intermediate file <code>mean.dat</code> can be <em>passed directly
      between the two services</em> (i.e. without being downloaded by the client)
      with a small change to the script:</p>
      <source>calc_mean input*.dat -o mean.dat.sgsref
plot -i mean.dat.sgsref -o graph.gif</source>
      </subsection>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Getting Started">
    <p>Download and install the JStyx software, as described on the <a href="../downloads.html">downloads</a>
    page.  Then follow the Styx Grid Services <a href="tutorial/index.html">tutorial</a>.</p>
    </section>
    
    <section name="Further reading">
    <p>Here are some publications about the SGS system in (roughly) decreasing order of
    usefulness:</p>
    <p>Jon Blower, Andrew Harrison, Keith Haines, <strong>Styx Grid Services: Lightweight, easy-to-use
middleware for scientific workflows</strong>, accepted for oral presentation at the <em>International Conference on Computer Science</em> 2006,
and for publication in <em>Lecture Notes in Computer Science</em>.
<a href="http://www.resc.rdg.ac.uk/publications/Blower_et_al_ICCS06.pdf">[download paper]</a></p>
    <p>Jon Blower, Keith Haines, Ed Llewellin, <strong>Styx Grid Services: lightweight, easy-to-use middleware for e-Science</strong>,
Presented in the UK e-Science booth at <em>SuperComputing</em>, Seattle, 15-17 November 2005
<a href="http://www.resc.rdg.ac.uk/publications/sgs_sc2005_talk.pdf">[download presentation]</a>
<a href="http://www.resc.rdg.ac.uk/publications/posters/sgs_poster_SC2005.pdf">[download poster]</a></p>
    <p>Jon Blower, Keith Haines, Ed Llewellin, <strong>Data streaming, workflow and firewall-friendly Grid Services with Styx</strong>,
<em>Proceedings of the UK e-Science All Hands Meeting</em> 19-22 September 2005
<a href="http://www.resc.rdg.ac.uk/publications/Blower_AHM_2005.pdf">[download paper]</a> <a href="http://www.nesc.ac.uk/talks/ahm2005/573.pdf">[download presentation]</a></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
