<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jdb@mail.nerc-essc.ac.uk">Jon Blower</author>
    <title>Downloads</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Downloading and installing JStyx">
      <p>The process of installing the JStyx software (which includes the
      <a href="sgs/index.html">Styx Grid Services</a> software) is very simple
      on all platforms.  In summary:
      <ul>
          <li>Install a Java runtime environment and add the <code>java</code>
          program to your PATH.</li>
          <li>Download the JStyx distribution and unpack it.</li>
          <li>Add the <code>bin</code> directory of the distribution to
          your PATH.</li>
      </ul>
      You can either follow the instructions below or just go straight to the
      <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=131424&amp;package_id=144157&amp;release_id=406792">downloads page</a>
      if you are impatient! ;-)
      </p>
    </section>
      <section name="1. Set up Java">
      <p>JStyx is a set of Java classes and so we need a Java runtime environment
      to run the software:</p>
      <ol>
          <li>Download and install a Java runtime environment version 1.4.2 or
          above from <a href="http://java.sun.com">here</a>.</li>
          <li>Add the <tt>bin</tt> directory of the Java installation to your <tt>PATH</tt>
              environment variable.</li>
          <li>Test this by opening a new terminal window or command prompt and typing <tt>java -version</tt>.
              The version number of the Java installation should be printed to the console.
              This should work from any directory on your system.</li>
      </ol>
      </section>
      <section name="2. Install JStyx">
      <p>
      The JStyx software is essentially the same on all platforms because it consists
      of a set of platform-independent Java libraries.  The only difference between
      the different distributions is the scripts that are used to launch JStyx
      programs (these scripts are .bat files under Windows and shell scripts under Unix
      and are found in the <code>bin/</code> directory of the distribution).
      </p>
      
      <subsection name="Windows">
      <p>
      <ol>
          <li>Download the software in zip format from
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/jstyx/jstyx-0.2.0-win.zip?download">here</a>.</li>
          <li>Unzip the software into the directory of your choice (e.g. <code>C:\JStyx</code>).</li>
          <li>Append the <code>bin</code> directory of the JStyx distribution to your PATH environment variable.</li>
      </ol>
      Note: to set an environment variable in Windows, right-click on &quot;My Computer&quot;
      and click the &quot;Advanced&quot; tab.  Click on &quot;Environment Variables&quot;.
      A Google search will reveal more information if you need it.
      </p>
      </subsection>
      
      <subsection name="Unix/Linux">
      <p>
      (Note: these instructions might also work on Mac OSX, but this hasn't been tested yet.)
      <ol>
          <li>Download the software as a gzipped tar archive from
            <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/jstyx/jstyx-0.2.0-unix.tar.gz?download">here</a>.</li>
          <li>Unpack the software into the directory of your choice
              (e.g. <code>cd /home/jon/JStyx; tar xzf jstyx-0.2.0-unix.tar.gz</code>).</li>
          <li>Append the <code>bin</code> directory of the JStyx distribution to
              your PATH environment variable.  You will probably want to do this
              in your login script (e.g. <code>~/.bashrc</code> or <code>~/.cshrc</code>)
              so that this is set automatically every time you log in.</li>
      </ol>
      If you use the C shell you can set an environment variable like this:
      <code>setenv PATH ${PATH}:/home/jon/JStyx/bin</code>.
      </p>
      </subsection>
      </section>
      
      <section name="3. Test the installation">
      <p>
      To verify that your installation is working, open a new terminal window
      (or command prompt) and enter <code>SGSRun</code> with no arguments.  If all
      is well, you should just see a usage message:
      </p>
      <source>Usage: SGSRun &lt;hostname&gt; &lt;port&gt; &lt;servicename&gt; [args]</source>
      <p>
      If you get an error message saying that the <code>SGSRun</code> program cannot
      be found, you have not set your PATH correctly.  If you get an error message 
      saying &quot;NoClassDefFoundError&quot; you have not set your JSTYX_HOME
      environment variable correctly.
      </p>
      </section>
      
      <section name="Access to source code">
      <p>You can get a source distribution from
      <a href="http://prdownloads.sourceforge.net/jstyx/jstyx-0.2.0-src.zip?download">here</a>.
      The build-instructions.txt file in this distribution contains instructions
      on how the software can be built from this source.</p>

      <p>If you want the very latest version of the source code (bearing in mind
      that it probably will not have been tested properly, if at all!) you can
      get the code from Sourceforge's Subversion server at
      https://svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/jstyx/trunk/core.  Anybody can download
      the entire code base, but only developers can check changes
      back in.
      </p>
      </section>
  </body>
</document>
