<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jdb@mail.nerc-essc.ac.uk">Jon Blower</author>
    <title>Styx Grid Services Tutorial: More configuration options</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Styx Grid Services Tutorial: More configuration options">
    <p>Normally you will not need to change the configuration file to follow this
    tutorial.  However sometimes this is necessary to fit in with your system.</p>
    
    <subsection name="Changing the port number of the server">
    <p>By default, the SGS server will run under port 9092.  If this is not 
    acceptable to you for any reason, you can change this in the configuration file.
    Look at the config file provided with the JStyx distribution (<code>SGSconfig.xml</code>).
    Before the part that contains the details of all the services, there is a section
    for configuring the server:</p>
    <source><![CDATA[<server port="9092"></server>]]></source>
    <p>Simply change the port number in this section to the number of your choice
    (the range of port numbers that you are allowed to choose 
    is system-dependent).</p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Changing the location of cached files">
    <p>While a Styx Grid Service is running, it creates a number of files on the
    server's hard disk.  These files are mostly cached copies of the input and
    output files.  By default, these files are kept in a directory called 
    <code>StyxGridServices</code> in the home directory of the user that is 
    running the SGS server (this is detected through Java's <code>user.home</code>
    system property.  Under Unix-type systems this will be <code>$HOME</code>
    and under Windows it will be <code>C:\Documents and Settings\username</code>.)</p>
    <p>If you would prefer these cached files to be kept elsewhere you can set this
    in the configuration file, for example:</p>
    <source><![CDATA[<server port="9092" cacheLocation="/usr/local/sgs/cache"></server>]]></source>
    <p>The <code>cacheLocation</code> must be a directory.  If it does not already
    exist it will be created. You must make sure that the user that is running the
    SGS server has write permissions in this directory.</p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Enabling logging messages">
    <p>(For developers only, really.)  The logging behaviour of the system is
    controlled by the <code>log4j.properties</code> file in the <code>conf</code>
    directory of the distribution.  To see debug messages for a particular class,
    change the logging level of that class to DEBUG.  You can see the individual
    Styx messages that are exchanged between client and server by setting the 
    logging levels of the StyxServerProtocolHandler and StyxConnection to
    DEBUG.  This is not recommended as it will significantly slow down the system.</p>
    </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
