<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jdb@mail.nerc-essc.ac.uk">Jon Blower</author>
    <title>Styx Grid Services Tutorial: Hello World application</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Styx Grid Services Tutorial: Hello World">
    <p>In this first part of the tutorial we shall wrap the traditional
    &quot;Hello World&quot; program as a Styx Grid Service and execute it remotely.
    In order to do this we need to go through the following steps:
    <ol>
        <li>Create a machine-readable description of the program (the configuration file).</li>
        <li>Create and run the SGS server, using this description.</li>
        <li>Run the service using the SGS client software.</li>
    </ol>
    </p>
    
    <subsection name="Creating the configuration file">
    <p>The first thing that we need to do is to create a configuration file that
    contains a complete description of the HelloWorld program.  The HelloWorld
    program reads no input files or command line arguments and simply prints a
    &quot;Hello World&quot; message to the console (i.e. to the standard output stream).
    </p>
    <p>The configuration file for this service is therefore very simple.  The
    JStyx distribution contains not only a suitable configuration file, but also
    a <a href="../../xref/uk/ac/rdg/resc/jstyx/gridservice/tutorial/HelloWorld.html">HelloWorld program</a>,
    implemented in Java.  The configuration file provided in the JStyx distribution
    contains descriptions of all the Styx Grid Services that are included in this
    tutorial but we are only interested in the HelloWorld service for the moment.
    Here is the relevant part of the configuration file, which is called <tt>SGSconfig.xml</tt>
    and is found in the <tt>conf</tt> directory of the JStyx distribution:</p>
    <source>
<![CDATA[<gridservice name="helloworld"
    command="JStyxRun uk.ac.rdg.resc.jstyx.gridservice.tutorial.HelloWorld"
    description="Prints Hello World to stdout">
  <outputs>
    <output type="stream" name="stdout"/>
  </outputs>
</gridservice>]]>
    </source>
    <p>This simply specifies that the HelloWorld program is run using the command
    &quot;<tt>JStyxRun uk.ac.rdg.resc.jstyx.gridservice.tutorial.HelloWorld</tt>&quot;
    and that it prints data on its standard output stream.  (<em>Important note for
    Windows users: the JStyxRun &quot;program&quot; is actually a batch file
    and so cannot be run with this command.  You will need to change the <tt>command</tt>
    property to &quot;cmd.exe /C JStyxRun uk.ac. ...&quot;.</em>)</p>
    </subsection>
    
    <subsection name="Run the server">
    
    </subsection>
    
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
