<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jdb@mail.nerc-essc.ac.uk">Jon Blower</author>
    <title>Styx Grid Services Tutorial</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Styx Grid Services Tutorial: Introduction">
    <p>This tutorial will guide you through the process of creating Styx Grid
    Services from command-line programs and using them in a number of ways.
    Before you start the tutorial you must install the JStyx software as 
    instructed <a href="../../downloads.html">here</a>.  No further software is required
    to follow this tutorial: all the Styx Grid Services software is included in
    the JStyx distribution.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Basic concepts">
    <p>In order to create a Styx Grid Service from an existing command-line
    program you need to write a short, machine-readable description of the
    program, including the input files it expects, the output files it produces
    and the command-line arguments it understands.  This description is known as
    the &quot;configuration file&quot; and is written
    in XML.  A full description of the format of this file can be found
    <a href="../config.html">here</a>, but for the moment you don't need to 
    worry about this: the tutorial material includes an example configuration file
    and this is all we need for this tutorial.</p>
    <p>Having created the configuration file, you will simply run a program
    that reads the file and automatically creates the Styx Grid Services server.
    You can then run <em>any</em> Styx Grid Service from the command line using
    a generic client program.</p>
    </section>
    <section name="Tutorial contents">
      <p>
      You can follow this tutorial online or, if you
      prefer to work from a printed copy, you can download a <a href="../../jstyx.pdf">PDF version</a>
      of this entire website.  The tutorial sections are:
      <ul>
        <li><a href="HelloWorld.html">The traditional &quot;Hello World&quot; application as a Styx Grid Service</a></li>
      </ul>
      </p>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
